Organizations, as well as
employees, can benefit from
creating a thoughtfully
designed, accessible workspace.
It opens up a creative sandbox
where people are free to
think, work and create in a
way that works best for them.
Inclusive recruiting.
For people on the neurodiversity spectrum,
interviews can be a challenge because
their communication styles are not similar
to those of neurotypical candidates.
The robust communication and eye contact
that recruiters and employers look for is
not the strong suit of
candidates on the spectrum.
Try to diversify your hiring strategy.
Psychometric assessments
are far more objective
as they eliminate human biases
in early stages of recruitment.
Provide multiple opportunities to
candidates so that they can demonstrate
their ability and competency during the
process, regardless of neurodiversity.
Formalize a hiring
program to help create a
talent pipeline of
neurodivergent candidates.
Distraction-free environment.
Provide a distraction-free
workspace to employees.
For example, noise-canceling headphones to
reduce sensory overload and spacious
drawers and storage cabinets
to declutter their desks.
Distraction need not
necessarily be physical.
Mental decluttering
is also as important.
Provide reference materials, worksheets,
and interview questions in advance and
have sufficient mental health
days in your company calendar.
Assistive technologies can help some
neurodivergent employees to perform better.
Such support can include software and
devices like portable and talking word
processors, assistive listening
systems, and visual organizers.
Architectural accommodations.
You can create focused areas of work where
employees, neurodiverse or neurotypical,
can choose to work
with low stimuli.
Assess the texture of desks, chairs,
and any other high-touch surfaces.
Spatial disorientation can frustrate
people with dyslexia and autism.
So try to create unique spaces with visual
landmarks and clear lines of sight that
can help everyone map their
own location within a space,
ultimately saving both
time and frustration.
Arranging furniture
in different ways can
also help people feel
better equipped at work.
The same positioning of the desk might
not be comfortable for everyone.
So allow a space where pacing is welcomed.
Flexibility.
Consider giving your employees
the option of remote working.
Flexible work schedules support
your entire workforce and not just
neurodivergent employees, working parents,
caregivers, and people with disability.
Empowering language.
Neurodiversity advocates encourage
inclusive, non-judgmental language.
While many disability advocacy
organizations prefer person-first
language, a person with autism,
a person with Down
syndrome, some research
has found that the majority
of the autistic community
prefers identity-first
language and autistic person.
Therefore, rather than making assumptions,
it's best to ask directly what a person's
preferred language is and how
they want to be addressed.
Educate your team.
Create a culture where
individuals feel comfortable to
disclose and talk openly
about their neurodiversity.
Upscale your workforce by providing
diversity and inclusion training days
for all so that everyone
understands the challenges
and the uniqueness
of neurodiversity.
Focus on fostering an open and trusting
relationship with your team.
Ask the employees what
support they need.
Provide employees additional
support and guidance if required.
And ensure to make employees aware
of the availability of the same.
Ensure other team
members are aware of the
specific needs each
individual may require.
Moreover, handle performance
issues very sensitively.
If you feel uncertain about anything,
you can begin by asking your employees
what they feel is required for them to
work efficiently and comfortably.
Your employees do not
have to reveal their medical
history for you to make
accommodations at the workplace.
You can simply ask them to share which
elements of their work experience
could be made more
inclusive or accessible.